Finding Aid for Alexander Winchell Papers, 1833-1891
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Reference and research files
  - Vanderbilt University
    - Student register circa 1877 (Box 19)
      (also includes scientific notes and lists of specimens) [former v. 224]
  - Wesleyan University (Box 19)
  - Wood (Box 19)
  - Zoology
    - Classification of species (Box 19)
    - Description of species and miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Lists of species (Box 19)
    - Michigan (Box 19)
    - References on American zoology (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 19)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series (Boxes 19-22) is divided into seven sections: "General" (1855-1890), "Personal" (1847-1890), "Souvenirs of European travels" (1873-1874), "State" (1857-1890), " Syracuse University" (1872-1876), " University of Michigan" (1855-1890), and " Vanderbilt University" (1878-1880). Except for the "Souvenirs of European travels" these scrapbooks are chronological, indexed, collections of clippings prepared to document Winchell's activities and interests. Winchell read, and clipped, widely. The "University of Michigan" scrapbooks, especially, can be a valuable source for the history of the University in that time period. The "Vanderbilt University" scrapbook covers the controversy over Winchell's firing and his views on the origin of humanity. The "Souvenirs of European travels" contains only tickets, receipts, and other memorabilia of his European tour, with little research value.
  - General
    - (v. 1) 1855-1869 (Box 19)
      [former v. 264]
    - (v. 2) 1869-1875 (Box 19)
      [former v. 265]
    - (v. 3, includes index) 1876-1879 (Box 19)
      [former v. 266] (microfilmed)
    - (v. 4, includes index) 1879-1884 (Box 20)
      [former v. 267]
    - (v. 5) 1884-1890 (Box 20)
      [former v. 268]
    - Index to v. 1, 2, and 5 (Box 20)
  - Personal
    - 1847-1853 (Box 20)
      (titled Excerpta miscellanea) [former v. 255]
    - (v. 1) 1854-1866 (Box 20)
      [former v. 256]
    - (v. 2) 1866-1874 (Box 20)
      [former v. 257]
    - (v. 3) 1874-1883 (Box 20)
      [former v. 258]
    - (v. 4) 1883-1884 (Box 20)
      [former v. 259]
    - (v. 5) 1884-1890 (Box 21)
      [former v. 260]
    - Loose clippings from v. 5 (Box 21)
    - Index to v. 1-5 (Box 21)
  - Souvenirs of European travels 1873-1874
    [former v. 262] (microfilmed)
    - Loose items from Souvenirs of European travels (Box 21)
  - State
    (also titled Facts about Michigan, mostly concerning its geology, natural history and resources)
    - (v. 1) 1857-1869 (Box 21)
      [former v. 275]
    - (v. 2) 1870-1872 (Box 21)
      [former v. 276]
    - (v. 3) 1872-1890 (Box 21)
      [former v. 277]
  - Syracuse University, 1872-1876 (Box 21)
    (includes index) [former v. 261] (microfilmed)
  - University of Michigan (Box 22)
    - (v. 1) 1855-1864 (Box 22)
      [former v. 270]
    - (v. 2) 1864-1872 (Box 22)
      [former v. 271]
    - (v. 3) 1872-1877 (Box 22)
      [former v. 272]
    - (v. 4, includes index) 1877-1879 (Box 22)
      [former v. 273]
    - (v. 5) 1879-1890 (Box 22)
      [former v. 274]
    - Index to v. 1-3 and 5 (Box 22)
  - Vanderbilt University, 1878-1880 (Box 22)
    [former v. 263]
- Visual materials
  The bulk of the Visual materials series (Box 23) is made up of illustrations from Winchell's books. Also included are a collection of fossil sketches by C. P. Whitfield, sketches by N. H. Winchell from the Michigan Geological Survey, plans for Winchell's house, portraits of Winchell, and miscellaneous scientific drawings.
  - Architectural and engineering drawings (Box 23)
  - Astronomy, Miscellaneous illustrations (Box 23)
  - Drawings, v. 1 1874 (Box 23)
    [chiefly landscape sketches of European trip] [former v. 245]
  - Drawings and maps from European trip 1874-1875 (Box 23)
  - Geology
    - Maps and sections (Box 23)
    - Sketches made by N. H. Winchell Michigan Geological Survey, 1869-1870 (Box 23)
    - Sketches for Minnesota Geological Survey, 1886-1887 (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous drawings (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous illustrations (Box 23)
  - House photographs (Box 23)
  - Illustrations for Geological studies 1886, 3 folders (Box 23)
  - Illustrations for Sketches of creation 1870 (Box 23)
  - Paleontology
    - Fossil types, drawings by C. P. Whitfield, 1 portfolios (Box 23)
    - Sketches (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous illustrations (Box 23)
  - Portraits
    - Drawings (Box 23)
    - Photographs (Box 23)
  - Sketch book (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 23)
- Processing notes
  The Processing notes series (Box 23) is made up of notes made during processing of this collection during the 1930s by the Historical Records Survey. They include the beginnings of a calendar of correspondence, biographical notes about Winchell's correspondents, genealogical material, and other notes.
  - Correspondence notes (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 23)
- Card files
  The Card files series (Box 24) includes files that belong with various topics in the Reference and research files series, but were separated because of their size.
  - Desiderata for library (Box 24)
  - Dictionary of crystallography and physical mineralogy (Box 24)
  - List of rock formations (Box 24)
  - Questions for geological sketches (Box 24)
- Maps
  Winchell was not a great mapmaker, but the collection contains a number of sketch maps made in the course of his work, as well as several maps made by N. H. Winchell for the Michigan Geological Survey. Appendix I to this finding aid lists each map found in the collection. Winchell's published maps are individually cataloged in the MHC map collection.
  - Maps (Folder Ac)
Maps found in the Winchell Papers
Maps found in field books (Box 7)
[Washtenaw County, 1859?]. 10 x 11 cm.
Washtenaw County
Vol. 3, flyleaf
Conjectural outline of coal basin between Barry and Woodville, [1859]. 14 x 18 cm.
Jackson County
Vol. 3, at Halt 156 (unnumbered pages)
Outline of Mackinaw I., [1860]. 14 x 9 cm.
Mackinac County
Vol. 7, p. [5]
Portion of Caledonia, Shiawasee Co., [1860]. 10 x 13 cm.
Shiawassee County
Vol. 7, at halt 946 (unnumbered pages)
[Knox County, Ohio, 1866]. 10 x 11 cm.
Ohio
Vol. 15, p. 22-23
Boothroyd's land, 50 acres, Avon Pt., Lorain Co. O., [1867]. 16 x 10 cm.
Ohio
Vol. 18, p. 64
[Vermilion Lake and Eagle Nest Lakes, Minnesota, 1886]. 4 maps, 9 x 9 cm.
Minnesota
Geological Survey of Minnesota, v. 1, 1886, p. 1, 5, 17, 21
[Northeastern Minnesota, 1887?]. 16 x 58 cm.
Minnesota
Geological Survey of Minnesota, v. 2, 1887, front fly leaf
North part Sea Gull Lake, Ts. 66-5 and 4, [1887]. 8 x 10 cm.
Minnesota
Geological Survey of Minnesota, v. 2, 1887, p. 38
Maps found in "Handwritten transcription of field books, 1859 Apr. 1-1860 Sept. 7, with scattered additions through 1866 (Michigan Geological Survey)" (Box 7)
Map of the vicinity of the Plumb Creek Quarries, [1859]. 15 x 23 cm.
Monroe County
Outline of coast between Brest and Point aux Peaux, [1859]. 7 x 8 cm.
Monroe County
p. 29
Sketch of diluvial markings at Stoney Point, [1859]. 15 x 21 cm.
Monroe County
p. 31
NW 1/4 Sec. 35 Sandstone, [1859]. 8 x 8 cm.
Jackson County
p. 79
N. part of section 36 township of Sandstone, Jackson Co. Mich., [1859]. 25 x 12 cm.
Jackson County
p. 86-87
[Parts of Sandstone, Spring Arbor, Blackman, and Summit Townships, Jackson County, 1859]. 37 x 98 cm.
Jackson County
between p. 102 and 103
[Jackson County, showing route of survey, 1859]. 31 x 38 cm.
Jackson County
between p. 102 and 103
Topography on county line between Jackson and Hillsdale Counties, [1859]. 18 x 22 cm.
Hillsdale County and Jackson County
p. 137
[Land ownership along the Flint River from Flint to about Montrose, 1859]. 35 x 52 cm.
Genesee County
between p. 250 and 251
S.E. qr. Sec. 26, town of Flushing Genesee Co., [1859]. 15 x 13 cm.
Genesee County
p. 253
[Distribution of sandy and clayey soils in Washtenaw and Lenawee Counties, 1860]. 17 x 20 cm.
Lenawee County and Washtenaw County
p. 269
[Region around Copper Bay, Ontario, 1860]. 11 x 13 cm.
Ontario
p. 417
[Spit of land in section 31, T 28 N, R 10 W, 1860]. 11 x 7 cm.
Grand Traverse County
p. 469
Portion of Caledonia Shiawassee Co., [1860]. 11 x 13 cm.
Shiawassee County
p. 484
Maps found in Visual materials series (Box 23) In "Drawings and maps from European trip, 1874-1875" folder
Alpine regions and passes, [1874?]. 13 x 13 cm.
Switzerland
90 miles square [Oberland and surrounding region], 1875. 15 x 15 cm.
Switzerland
Regions of the High Alps, 1874. 10 x 13 cm.
Switzerland
Six miles square [Mont blanc region], 1875. 13 x 13 cm.
Switzerland
In "Geology, Maps and sections" folder
Chautauqua County, 1876. 17 x 15 cm.
New York
Excursions [in Alabama, 1852]. 15 x 18 cm.
Alabama
Map of part of the Huronian Region, [1890]. 15 x 32 cm.
Ontario
Township 27 North 11 West [Michigan, showing land ownership, 1865]. 14 x 15 cm.
Grand Traverse County
In "Geology, Sketches made by N. H. Winchell, Michigan Geological Survey, 1869-1870" folder
[Mouth of Manistee River, 1869]. 12 x 19 cm.
Manistee County
Map of halt 1045 [Black Lake, 1869]. 12 x 19 cm.
Presque Isle County
Map of halt 1062, Bien Fete Pt., [1869]. 19 x 12 cm.
Mackinac County
Map of halt 1077, N. shore L. Mich., [1869]. 7 x 10 cm.
Schoolcraft County
Map of halt 1080, Pt. Seul Choix, N. shore of L. Mich., [1869]. 12 x 20 cm.
Schoolcraft County
Map of the basin of Sunken Lake, [1869]. 12 x 19 cm.
Presque Isle County
Map of Fayette Harbor [1869]. 20 x 14 cm.
Delta County
N. end of Middle Island (halt 1300) showing wave-formed beaches, [1869]. 19 x 12 cm.
Alpena County
Part of Thunder Bay River, [1869]. 10 x 12 cm.
Alpena County
In "Geology, Sketches for Minnesota Geological Survey, 1886-1887" folder
T 65 N, R 3 W, Minn.,[1887?]. 7 x 11 cm.
Minnesota
Maps found in oversize folder (Ac)
[Coal diggings along Sandstone Creek, Michigan, 1859?]. on sheet 40 x 25 cm., both sides
Jackson County
[Coal regions of West Virginia, 18--]. 2 maps on sheet 43 x 28 cm.
West Virginia
County of Alcona, Town 26 N, Range 8 E, [showing gas springs, 18--]. 30 x 30 cm.
Alcona County
[Garden plantings, 18--]. 39 x 67 cm.
Washtenaw County
Location of Former Folder and Volume Numbers
1-75 Boxes 1-3
76 dispersed under topics
77 Box 7
78-82 Box 1
83-84 Box 10
85-170 Boxes 8-10 (some dispersed under topics, a few discarded as duplicate)
171-219 Boxes 14-19 (dispersed under topics)
220-221 dispersed under topics
222-224 Box 23
1-13 discarded (duplicate material)
14-15 portfolios, not vols.: some material discarded, some in Box 1
16-22 discarded (duplicate material)
23 a portfolio, not a vol.: Box 23
24 discarded (duplicate material)
25 portfolio, not vol.: Box 17
26-71 dispersed under topics in earlier processing or returned to donor
72 a box, not a vol.: most in Box 24
73 Box 6
74 Box 18
75-76 Box 6
77 Box 7
78-80 Box 6
80a Box 6
81 Box 6
82 missing or never received
83-86 Box 6
87 Box 7
88-91 Box 6
92 Box 7
93-113 Box 6
114-153 Box 7
154 Box 3
155-162 Box 4
163-164 Box 5
165-168 Box 3
169 Box 7
170-177 Box 5
178 Box 16
179 Box 16
180 Box 7
181-182 Box 16
183-185 Box 11
186 Box 10
187-189 Box 11
190-191 Box 17
192 Box 15
193 Box 17
194 Box 14
195-197 Box 9
198 Box 14
199 Box 8
200 Box 10
201-202 Box 14
203 Box 15
204-210 Box 12
211-218 Box 13
219-221 Box 14
222 Box 18
223 Box 7
224 Box 19
225 Box 9
226 Box 10
227 Box 18
228 Box 15
229 Box 18
230 Box 15
231-232 Box 14
233 Box 15
234 Box 17
235 Box 15
236 Box 5
237 Box 18
238-239 Box 19
240 Box 15
241-242 Box 19
243 Box 16
244 discarded
245 Box 23
246 Box 14
247-248 Box 5
249-250 Box 18
251-252 Box 17
253 Box 15
254 Box 18
255-259 Box 20
260-263 Box 21
264-266 Box 19
267-268 Box 20
269 Box 15
270-277 Box 21
278 Box 18
279 Box 19
280 Box 14
281 discarded
282 Box 5
283 Box 7
284 Box 23